so short suitor that I'm interested to
your thoughts on it's the OOD ala
chapter 7 the eighth two days about
catch Anna so on one occasion the Buddha
was living in savatthi in jeta's would
in an Asif indicas park now on that
occasion the venerable maja catch anna
was sitting not far from the buddha
having crossed his legs keeping his body
upright having properly set of
recollected nests of the body internally
and then it would pemmican which so
internally means properly recollected
the mount very firmly the mother is the
representative of the body if you are
mindful of the entry points of the body
mm-hmm with the mind converges
yes it's funny because those two words
are jet time and Perry mocking but quite
clearly adverbs the boat together that
they're both describing mmm having set
up properly set up manifested the body
in this way magic time Parimal so our
Jets hanging so the reason why I did
Forellis because it's not about
attending to your mouth right about
watching sensations and your lips or
something that's not what mouth is by
the way your mouth is not your lips yeah
so why would you be concentrating on
your upper lip or whatever yeah
ask yourself what is my mouth yeah okay
so it has the physical aspect but what
is the significance of that physical
aspect so the whole thing that's what
mouth is so the physical side of it with
the whole significance of it yeah
consumption again point of relationship
with the world pretty much a very
personal thing consumption internally
the speech expression communication
relation everything converges on the
mouth you taking up the mouth in that
manner as in being ignorant of its
nature means you take up the entire body
or body the aspect of the mouth which is
what the body is so it's almost like the
the mouth is the like first twenty
contact the pretty much yes as I said
before it's a point converging between
like what's obviously mental yeah and
what's obviously physical well this is
that in-between where you are sort of
muddled about yeah like how can your
thoughts enter your mouth yeah
yet you are speaking of this fact you're
my heart is open your mouth is almost
more your thoughts than any other part
of your body it seems to me that's is
where the conceiving have yeah you
regard your mouth as internally very
thoroughly as that which actually
belongs to the mental but he doesn't I
think also I'm right in saying that
there's so much more muscular like
physical muscular control around the
mouth they sure joke about it the way we it is
they sure joke about it the way we it is
what animals even more so the entire
existence revolves around the mouth
touch communicate do everything is going
to mouth more often do not so if you so
it's one way in which you can be mindful
of the body
hmm so PI peripherally disowning the
image the image of the mouth yep
and then for you while you're doing that
and that mouth stands for the body
exec and that's what it's meant in those
like anapanasati Souter yeah which is
whatever body there that he discerns
through his directness of breathing yeah
that's what the body is for him yeah
yeah that's one body in the body what is
basically that is what your body is yes
but by using that point what is that
point for using using using the mouth as
the body hmm just um yeah yeah just down
to the body your you're choosing
something like the most fundamental link
between the mind and the body when
you're choosing you well so why the
mouth why my parent were mouth well
because the mouth just happens to be
yeah this it has to be something this
most fundamental primal primal hmm
connection or not connection but place
where they do kill yeah well even yeah
like primal but in a sense natural way
of sort of relating between the point of
view and the body good because as you
know in the other suitors it said the
body paired with consciousness
consciousness is not in the body
yeah no the body is in the consciousness
it's just two simultaneous things and
their relationship results in the entire
nama Rupa pretty much that you can
anything adequacy feel intend is the
result of consciousness pair with the
body or body in constant being there and
that whole relationship between body and
consciousness is inconceivable to you
because if you were to conceive how is
your body conscious or how the constant
has the body they would imply that you
can step outside of the those aggregates
and see how they relate that in you are
fully within so the way this
relationship is of the five aggregates
is that like mental and material so to
speak superimposed together and
perception feeling intentions they're
all already points of converging so to
speak action on account of mental in
regard to physical action are kind of
physically engulfed mental so net if you
look at it phenomenologically they're
gonna be some points with these things
converge yeah where the taking up of the
body happens first and like why is it
the mouth it's quite an airy and
eleven question because if it's not that
it would have been something else but
why it was probably revolves around the
whole you know need for food hunger
breastfeeding as a baby the first
basically point of pleasure entrance
into the world is through your mouth
it's a kid as a toddler you're
completely unaware of your limbs and
everything else but you have awareness
that's what your mind is and then you
kind of grow from there but not at the
expense of it but through it in other
words that framework of your mouth being
the point of the laser remains in the
area so you can only prove you can
proliferate infinitely so within that
framework yeah and then usually becomes
more exactly because it's the pleasure
that governs the direction of your
proliferation if the mind is ignorant
which every mind is in the beginning you
go after pleasure so every point of of
pleasure will kind of create a channel
for possible proliferation so your mouth
being the main point but then within
that you know once say you're not
starving you don't go hungry you eat five times a
you don't go hungry you eat five times a
day you completely you stop seeing it
you stop seeing the point of pleasure
being your mouth and you start looking
further yeah that's the way the whole
sexuality comes in the groin that's so
literally in that suit up
Anand I was teaching Ted none when he
said it's it's the bridge yeah so sexual
instruction the bridge but she compared
it basically to the food you have to eat
yeah and you can't stop eating yes
so the food for your point of contact of
what the mouth is is what the food is
but the food for the point of contact of
growing is sexual integration so it's
the same thing in a way just one is
proliferated further yeah but it's the
same principle and theoretically you
could understand that principle but not
before you actually stop providing food
for the ground literally so that we said
like no this this food is necessary sure
so as a principle the food is necessary
to some extent but not to the extent of
of sexual integral that must be a band
there is absolutely no justification for
it but then you can't just stop eating
food then in order to do the principal
on the level of the mouth now you can't
stop having sexual intercourse and you
will undo the principle of depending on
the own sexual pleasure but you can't do
that to the food cause it's it's much
more fundamental and that's why again as
we spoke into this routine the first
jhana the at that you can't speak yeah
as in the speech has subsided yeah
because you're not taking up the mount
mouth to the point of actual
possibilities of breaking into speech
and that's when the first jhana sexual
sexuality or any sensuality becomes
inconceivable you're fully secluded from
it because if you're not taking up your
mouth in such manner
how can you mind proliferate further to
the other parts of convergence of
pleasure on account of body yeah
inconceivable so that's right so so this
pairing mocking word which is usually
translated as just in front hmm it's I
think it only appears in this stop
phrase with my front with mindfulness
yeah and but it but it is different
types of my mindfulness in the body of
mindfulness because again it's the
mindfulness is the recollect Nisour the
same thing yeah that that if we to think
of it as primal congress which is what
it is literally a parry around mocking
mouth around the mouth yeah again that's
what physical solitude was always like
the Buddha would urge monks because you
are not communicate yeah there's no chit
chat there's no speaking there's no
listening to the other because all those
things imply convergence point of your
mouth or whole domain of relationship
through through verbal yeah and although
although this like for example most of
these who don't talk about jhana
although one of them does but but if
this is to be understood as around the
mouth then it just definite all this
mindfulness is
how much more closely related to Jonah
then sure sure
well that's that's how it's firstly
related around the mouth means properly
mindful yeah mindful proper
representation of the phenomenon of the
body and your experience as a whole yeah
you can take that now in the direction
of Johnny you want because you can then
because it's on the basis of that same
direction activeness exactly yeah so
just twelve on particular
characteristics of that yeah oh you can
take to the direction of brahma because
as that city says yeah so you can take
in many other directions yeah properly
established established recollect
earnest of that which is which happens
to be the point of convergence between
your mind and your body yeah usually and
again like you see if you were to start
to think like what is messy as we said
before what is speech can you speech
when you speak or when you don't speak
is it speech the sound that comes out of
your mouth yeah is it speech your
thoughts being sort of you know solidify
into the verbal frequencies but how does
that work exactly
it's the air from my lungs that comes
through the throat the only micro thing
so basically my speech is the air from
inside of me coming out and producing
vibrations so are my thoughts in my
belly and today it's ridiculous yet by
not thinking about it you kind of merge
it you merge the two together your
thoughts in your feet I cannot see how
they're two simultaneous phenomena not
completely separate like they cannot
possibly merge or relate it's just and
that's why as Buddha said having thought
important as in having thinking and
pondering they're enduring one breaks
into speech the thing is funny how they
I think it's the philosophic the
tradition philosophers I think since
Thomas Aquinas the this idea of to be
human is to be that talking animal the
rational animal languages like really
well it's the domain of yeah of thought
of reflection yeah of expression which
is kind of limited to well certainly
doesn't go love it into humans yeah
Ricardo Ramos might be
to communicate yet result but it's fast
on establishing a domain of of speech
these are significant so a whole what we
are is based on this idea of this
connection between the mind in the
mental file but magnify the mouth either
speak the mining the material the mind
and the material yeah yeah exactly yeah
and it's same with the food again
like you know you think look but
consuming food yeah but disappearing in
you you think like it's in you yeah but
the food is in the belly which is out
there with this table and this pot and
the food so the food is still closer to
where it was before then it's inside of
me yeah the whole notion of consumption
is like literally you are dead barrier
through which passes now it's in you but
oh wait there is no in me it's just a
point of view in regard to this whole
thing yeah and all that in its
peripheral to from what in regard to
what you're looking for that's what I
just add of the poly internal yes
literally at I mean significant it is
literally what what what peripheral is
that's why the more you develop it the
carnal less mine it sees it continues to
be a yeah so maybe we can say having
crossed it like this is marker Charlie
sitting having crossed his legs keeping
his body upright having properly set up
recollecting us of the body peripherally
around the mouth hmm
so the Buddha sees this
having seen the meaning of this on that
occasion he altered this utterance for
whoever and it's a verse for however
there is always recollected Ness
constantly established on the body it's
in the person inspired by what exactly
what I described so when I said mean
firefighter collecting this means
basically recognizing the image of the
body but it's not actually attending to
what you're perceiving which is the
result of the body being there yes your
perception of your own body is secondary
yeah can't serve it's always and
constantly always we've always record
for whoever there is always recollecting
this constantly stops on the body that
doesn't mean focusing on something body
body body yes no means like big
collectiveness the context yeah anything
that occurs is within it and fully full
discernment of that makes the context
imperturbable so it's always constantly there and then
so it's always constantly there and then
he says this because the body is always
constantly there yeah the way whether
you where do you want to have not really
aware about him so then he says it could
not be it could not be mine hmm it will
not be it will not be mine he who
regularly stays in that place at the
right time he crossed and destroyed all
the conceit
because as we just said when we started
this that mindfulness offers
peripherally the mouth is a convergence
point that's not speaking
he's mattress or the body yeah and it
you you trained in that kind of
peripheral image peripheral recognition
recollected miss you become familiar
with the nature of it and the nature of
their body is there like like a lump
collection like pile of elements like
other things that are around here that
are clearly not yours clearly cannot be
yours that's the point of that
the cryptic verse no no it does think
it's means likely not just that it's not
mine but even in the future things
cannot be any different so that things
could possibly become mine it's
inconceivable so not just that it could not be for me
so not just that it could not be for me
it won't be for me either way it cannot
be for me in the future because it's all
on the basis of this right now which is
unburnable so I mean basically it could
not be it means like okay so there's
this thing here but it could not be yeah
that's a first you had no saying the
thing that's here yeah so he could have
not been yeah it could have not been
here but whatever it is you won't be
mine or for me because again it came on
its own yeah so it's nothing other than
like full development of the principle
that already so define understand yes
and whatever is the nature to arise
that's why it's a nature to cease yeah
there's nothing it's not like cryptic
it's not like some Vedic old verse or
something it's just a description of an
each other yeah on a most more secular
level because there is absolutely not
even a slightest room yeah for the sense
of I am to remain lingering and in
regards to that we did know like could
have not been which means you know sane
it's arising so and if if it could have
if it's like it could not have been
manifested in which case there's no
there's no possibility for it to be mine
of course yeah
so that that possibility for it to be
mine isn't is not done through me it
just happens to be because that it
becomes possible because that things
happens to have manifested yeah which
which means does rubbish it it depends
upon something which I have no control
over so doesn't matter how much of it it
is felt as mine how much of it is mine
yeah fundamentally cannot be mine yeah
that's right yeah yeah because there is
no mind we don't think given beforehand
yeah there is no mind
so that that hole those those that whole
verse it's not it's it's it's it's not
like a description of a process of what
happens or how you have to reason it's
just a direct insight of whatever is of
the nature eyes that's why it's
impairment no because I wait for it to
see it disappear or because I apply my
said no it's because it has a reason on
its own yes that's why it will have it
simple that's why I cannot own it that's
it let's be explicit it here means but
the body we talked about is this
mindfulness the shoddy in mindfulness of
the correctness of the body body being
the necessary basis for everything yeah
your whole universe is within the body
within the basis of the body so that you
regard the body yes that which is just
could have not been as in I've not seen
it as much I are not I'm not it's master
with that means there is i cannot
entertain ownership even if I want to
yeah and that's automatically felt by the way
and that's automatically felt by the way
the absence of ownership yeah once you
see it correctly you don't need to then
go and take let go of your ownership on
account of what you understood your
understanding means letting go of the
ownership and that also will start to
pertain that to the possibility of the
future body as in later on you can see
if you're not completely free from doubt
like it might be apparent that now
nothing can be used but there is a still
tacit assumption record if things might
be different in the future to some
extent and to that extent to allow you
to own them yeah but now even the whole
domain not a particular possibility of
this so that but the main of the
possibility as if the nature of
possibilities has to be of the same
nature that it's unknowable because it's
it could have not been thus it won't be
for me whichever way it is yeah cannot
be for me even if I wanted to
and so regularly staying in that place
yeah clarifying recollecting and then clarify
clarifying recollecting and then clarify
what you recollected the context of the
body correctly which is that peripheral
recognition that the body is here see
I'm talking to you feeling like this
thinking that want to do that because
this body's here enduring is a necessary
basis for all these possibilities and
actual engagements so it's not about you
finding in like the particular points of
your body sensations and attending to it
because I think that in order to do that
you need to ignore the context yeah see
that's another act you're caught up in
am I telling this I'm pretending this
and feeling tension moving moving
whatever else no all of that is possible
because the body is there beforehand
already and that's where your
mindfulness is recollecting that right
order recollecting the correct image the
mind comes first because the right image
comes first that's that's the entire
point the clearly that becomes the
harder to lose it it will become the
harder to distract yourself from it it
will become and that means you're gonna
be your experience will be more and more
and more dispassionate yeah and at the
right time he crosses over attachment
yeah I think all of the conceits all the
attachments all the senses of ownership
or whatever else you've been sort of
entertaining however vaguely it ceased because you
however vaguely it ceased because you
stopped providing
fertile basis for it